Guide to the Josiah William Bailey Papers, 1833-1967, bulk 1900-1946 RL.00065
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Senatorial Series, 1930-1946, 436 boxes
  - Trade and Commerce Subseries, 1930-1946 (Box 177-216)
    - Commerce: Trade & Commerce, Rural Electrification Authority, 1940-1946, undated (Box 216)
    - Commerce: Trade & Commerce, undated (Box 216)
  - Banking and Currency Subseries, 1930-1946
    Correspondence, speeches, notes, and printed material concentrate on U. S. banking and monetary policy. The major portion of this section covers the period 1931-1935. Papers on banking relate to the banking crisis and governmental efforts to ease the situation through guarantees of bank deposits and to the various governmental loan agencies: the Home Loan Bank, the Federal Land Bank, and the Reconstruction Finance Corporation. There is considerable constituent mail concerning loans from these agencies. Monetary matters cover gold, silver, the devaluation of the dollar, currency stabilization, the regulation of the stock exchange, and bankruptcy legislation. During the early 1930s, there is correspondence concerning the financial affairs of the Wake County Savings Bank, of which Bailey was a vice president. Financial material on Bailey and Helen Leigh Bailey is dated during the early 1930s. Material is arranged chronologically by day.
    1932: Forming of the three loan agencies; Glass Banking Bill; Goldsborough Bill for currency stabilization; Stegall Bill guaranteeing bank deposits.
    1933: Constituent opinion on Federal guarantees of bank deposits; Glass-Stegall Banking Bill; World Economic Conference; Municipal Bankruptcy legislation
    1934: Bailey's speech, Our Monetary Policy; Sumner-Wilcox Municipal Bankruptcy Bill; Fletcher-Rayburn Bill to regulate the stock exchange.
    1935: Banking Act of 1935.
    1937: McAdoo Bill; Patman Banking Bill.
    1943: Insurance Bill, leaving regulation in the hands of the states.
    1944: Insurance Bill.
    - Banking & Currency, 1930, June-1932 (Box 217)
    - Banking & Currency, 1932, July-1933, Feb. (Box 218)
    - Banking & Currency, 1933, March-June 15 (Box 219)
    - Banking & Currency, 1933, June 16-1934, Jan. (Box 220)
    - Banking & Currency, 1934, Feb.-April (Box 221)
    - Banking & Currency, 1934, May-1935, Jan. (Box 222)
    - Banking & Currency, 1935, Feb.-Dec. (Box 223)
    - Banking & Currency, 1936, Jan.-1938, Dec. (Box 224)
    - Banking & Currency, 1939, Jan.-1941, Dec. (Box 225)
    - Banking & Currency, 1942, June-1944, June (Box 226)
    - Banking & Currency, 1944, June 11-1946, undated (Box 227)
  - Economy Subseries, 1931-1946 (Box 228-239)
    Correspondence, telegrams, speeches, notes, and printed material pertain to the economy of the United States. The material tends to be of a more general nature rather than relating to specific topics such as banking. The Depression, its causes and solutions, and governmental expenditures are the major topics covered in the early 1930's. Papers on the committee formed in 1935 to investigate the causes of the Depession are found in this section, although the bulk of this material is located in Trade and Commerce. The Business or Roosevelt depression of 1937-1938 is of primary importance in the material of the late 1930's.. Bailey was an outspoken critic of governmental attitudes toward spending and pump priming and believed that government should encourage private enterprise. He stated his beliefs in a speech known as the Declaration of Principles. Constituent opinion on governmental policies, Bailey's Declaration of Principles, and a statement by Roosevelt that the South was America's No. 1 Economic Problem are the main thrust of correspondence during the late 1930's. Material for the 1940's generally concerns efforts to control the ecoromy and prevent inflation through economy in government and price fixing. Material is arranged chronologically by day.
    - Economy, 1931-1932, June (Box 228)
    - Economy, 1932, July-1933, June 5 (Box 229)
    - Economy, 1933, June 6-1935, April 5 (Box 230)
    - Economy, 1935, April 6-1937, Aug. (Box 231)
    - Economy, 1937, Sept.-1938, May 15 (Box 232)
    - Economy, 1938, May 16-1939, May (Box 233)
    - Economy, 1939, June-1941, Nov. (Box 234)
    - Economy, 1941, Dec.-1942, April (Box 235)
    - Economy, 1942, May-Sept. (Box 236`)
    - Economy, 1942, Oct.-1945, June (Box 237)
    - Economy, 1945, July-1946, Dec., undated (Box 238)
    - Economy, undated (Box 239)
  - Tax and Tariff Subseries, 1930-1946 (Box 239-272)
    Largely correspondence and telegrams, the material consists mainly of constituent opinion on specific taxes and tariffs, predominantly the former. The bulk of the correspondence is from businessmen who were affected by the various taxes and tariffs. Frequently correspondents discussed in detail the expected or resulting effects of the tax or tariff on their businesses. Topics include income tax, sales tax, revenue bills, excess profits tax, and taxes and tariffs on specific comnodities. The material is arranged chronologically by month.
    - Tax & Tariff, 1930-1931 (Box 239)
    - Tax & Tariff, 1932, Jan.-April (Box 240)
    - Tax & Tariff, 1932, April-May (Box 241)
    - Tax & Tariff, 1932, June-1933, March (Box 242)
    - Tax & Tariff, 1933, April-1934, Feb. (Box 243)
    - Tax & Tariff, 1934, Feb.-March (Box 244)
    - Tax & Tariff, 1934, March-May (Box 245)
    - Tax & Tariff, 1934, June-1935, April (Box 246)
    - Tax & Tariff, 1935, April-May (Box 247)
    - Tax & Tariff, 1935, May-July (Box 248)
    - Tax & Tariff, 1935, May-1936, Feb. (Box 249)
    - Tax & Tariff, 1936, Feb.-May (Box 250)
    - Tax & Tariff, 1936, May-June (Box 251)
    - Tax & Tariff, 1936, June-1937, June (Box 252)
    - Tax & Tariff, 1937, July-1938, Jan. (Box 253)
    - Tax & Tariff, 1938, Jan.-March (Box 254)
    - Tax & Tariff, 1938, March-Sept. (Box 255)
    - Tax & Tariff, 1938, Oct.-1939, March (Box 256)
    - Tax & Tariff, 1939, April-Dec. (Box 257)
    - Tax & Tariff, 1940, Jan.-Aug. (Box 258)
    - Tax & Tariff, 1940, Sept.-1941, May (Box 259)
    - Tax & Tariff, 1941, June-Sept. (Box 260)
    - Tax & Tariff, 1941, Sept.-I942, March (Box 261)
    - Tax & Tariff, 1942, March-July (Box 262)
    - Tax & Tariff, 1942, July-Aug. (Box 263)
    - Tax & Tariff, 1942, Aug. (Box 264)
    - Tax & Tariff, 1942, Aug.-Sept. (Box 265)
    - Tax & Tariff, 1942, Sept.-Oct. (Box 266)
    - Tax & Tariff, 1942, Nov.-1943, May (Box 267)
    - Tax & Tariff, 1943, June-Dec. (Box 268)
    - Tax & Tariff, 1944, Jan.-May (Box 269)
    - Tax & Tariff, 1944, May-1945, July (Box 270)
    - Tax & Tariff, 1945, Aug.-1946 (Box 271)
    - Tax & Tariff, undated (Box 272)
  - Treasury Department Subseries, 1931-1946
    Correspondence and printed material relate to the various agencies and concerns of the Treasury Department. The section contains material pertaining to the Coast Guard, such as appointments, promotions, regulations and specific bills dealing with Coast Guard activities. There is also information on the functions and operation of the Federal Alcohol Unit. Also included is correspondence concerning the Internal Revenue Service (IRS) and its duties and constituent problems in dealing with the IRS. There are some papers relating to Bailey's personal income tax as well, although the bulk of this material is found in the Personal Series. Correspondence in the late 1930's deals with the attempts of the granite industry to have granite used in the construction of Federal buildings. There is information on currency stabilization and gold and silver in this section, as well as in Banking and Currency. The material is arranged chronologically by month.
    - Treasury Department, 1930, Jan-1932, Jan. (Box 272)
    - Treasury Department, 1932, Feb.-1934, May (Box 273)
    - Treasury Department, 1934, June-1936, March (Box 274)
    - Treasury Department, 1939, Jan.-April (Box 275)
    - Treasury Department, 1939, May-1941, July (Box 276)
    - Treasury Department, 1941, Aug.-1944, Dec. (Box 277)
    - Treasury Department, 1945-1946, undated (Box 278)
  - Education Subseries, 1931-1946
    Correspondence, telegrams and some printed material chiefly reflect constituent opinion on educational issues. The material during the early 1930's deals with the financial crises faced by many private educational institutions, particularly the Baptist-affiliated schools in which Bailey had a personal interest. Other papers for that period concern cuts in appropriations for vocational education and a proposed amendment to allow the Reconstruction Finance Corporation to aid colleges and universities. Correspondence in the late 1930's pertains to Federal aid to kindergartens and libraries. The main thrust of this section focuses on the all important issue of Federal aid to education and to state versus Federal control. This issue is the central one for the years 1939-1946. The continuation of the National Youth Administration (1943) and the school lunch program (1946) are also discussed in the correspondence. The material is arranged chronologically by day.
    - Education, 1930-1932, April (Box 278)
    - Education, 1932, May-1935, Feb. (Box 279`)
    - Education, 1935, March-1937 (Box 280)
    - Education, 1938-1940, Feb. 10 (Box 281)
    - Education, 1940, Feb. 11-1942, July (Box 282)
    - Education, 1942, Aug.-1943, June 20 (Box 283)
    - Education, 1943, June 21-Dec. (Box 284)
    - Education, 1944, Jan.-1945, April 15 (Box 285)
    - Education, 1945, April 16-30 (Box 286)
    - Education, 1945, May-1946, Dec., undated (Box 287)
  - Food and Drugs Subseries, 1931-1946
    Correspondence, telegrams, and printed material chiefly concern the various bills proposed by Congress relating to the advertisement and regulation of sales of different foods and drugs. While much of the correspondence is routine, there is a significant number of detailed letters by producers describing the expected results of proposed bills. The bulk of the material refers to the Tugwell Food and Drug Bill (1933) the Copeland and the Stephens Bills (1934), and the Copeland Bill (1935). Correspondence for the late 1930's concerns food and drug bills of lesser importance. There is little material for the 1940's. Material is arranged chronologically by month.
    - Food & Drug, 1931-1934 (Box 288)
    - Food & Drug, 1935-1938 (Box 289)
    - Food & Drug, 1939-1945, undated (Box 290)
  - Communism and Facism Subseries, 1931-1946
    Correspondence and printed material are chiefly concerned with communist and Nazi influence in the United States. The bulk of the material refers to the work of the Dies Committee on Un-American Activities, constituent opinion on the continuation of the committee, and to the question of U. S. aid to democratic Spain. There is also some hysterical material on communism and Nazism, particularly the former. Material is arranged chronologically by day.
    - Communism and Fascism, 1933-1939 (Box 290)
    - Communism and Fascism, 1939-1946 (Box 291)
  - Foreign Policy Subseries, 1931-1946
    Mainly letters, telegrams, and printed material chiefly concerning constituent opinion on major foreign policy issues. Although there is little material for the years 1931-1937, there is a considerable quantity pertaining to United States involvement in the World Court. Papers for 1938 concern the Spanish Civil War, the arms embargo, the Sino-Japanese war, and sales of scrap iron to Japan. Between the outbreak of World War II and the Japanese attack on Pearl Harbor, the principal topics of concern are the Neutrality Act, the Arms Embargo, aid to Finland and Great Britain, and keeping the United States out of the European war The material during the war years deals with efforts to establish a world organization for peace. There is also opinion on the Dumbarton Oaks proposal of 1945 and postwar aid to war-torn countries. Material pertaining to the conduct of the war and relations with U. S. allies is chiefly located in the National Defense section. Material is arranged chronologically by day.
    - Foreign Policy, 1931-1938, March (Box 291)
    - Foreign Policy, 1938, April-1939, Sept. 18 (Box 292)
    - Foreign Policy, 1939, Sept. 19-27 (Box 293)
    - Foreign Policy, 1939, Sept. 28-Oct. 27 (Box 294)
    - Foreign Policy, 1939, Oct. 38-1940, Aug. 7 (Box 295)
    - Foreign Policy, 1940, Aug. 8-1941, June (Box 296)
    - Foreign Policy, 1941, July-1944, Feb. 3 (Box 297)
    - Foreign Policy, 1944, Feb. 4-Dec. (Box 298)
    - Foreign Policy, 1945, Jan.-July (Box 299)
    - Foreign Policy, 1945, Aug. 1946, undated (Box 300)
    - World Court 1930-1938 (Box 300)
  - Jewish Concerns Subseries, 1931-1946 (Box 301-302)
    Correspondence, clippings, and printed material pertain to Jewish affairs. The major portion of the material, 1944-1946, deals with the Palestine question and the creation of a Jewish state. There is material on a White Paper published in the 1930s concerning attitudes toward Jews and information concerning German treatment of Jews in the 1930s and efforts to get Jews out of Germany. There is also anti-Semitic correspondence and printed material. Material is arranged chronologically by day.
    - Jewish Concerns, 1931, Nov.-1945, Sept. (Box 301)
    - Jewish Concerns, 1945, Oct.-1946, Nov., Printed Material (Box 302)
  - State Department and Immigration Subseries, 1931-1946
    Principally correspondence, this material relates to routine matters, such as obtaining passports and visas, receiving privilege of the port, and the entry of immigrants into the United States, More important topics on which there is information are claims against the German government, 1933; laws restricting immigration, 1935; the repeal of the Chinese excluxion Act, 1943; the nomination of Edward J. Flynn as ambassador to Australia, 1943; the postwar peace settlement, 1944; and a loan to Great Britain, 1946. Material is arranged chronologically by day.
    - State Department, 1930-1933, Aug. (Box 303)
    - State Department, 1933, Sept.-1936, Dec. (Box 304)
    - State Department, 1937-1939, May (Box 305)
    - State Department, 1939, June-1941, April (Box 306)
    - State Department, 1941, May-1943, June (Box 307)
    - State Department, 1943, July-1944, Nov. (Box 308)
    - State Department, 1944, Dec.-1946, undated (Box 309)
  - Department of the Interior Subseries, 1931-1946
    Correspondence and printed material are concerned with those matters under the jurisdiction of the Department of the Interior. One of the more important subjects found In this material is the development of national parks and battlegrounds, particularly the Great Smokey Mountain National Park and the Blue Ridge Parkway. There is information pertaining to the policies of the Bureau of Indian Affairs, principally dealing with North Carolina tribes and to legislation affecting Indians. Policies and legislation related to insular affairs - especially Puerto Rico and the Philippines, are covered in this section. There is also material dealing with the development of fisheries and mines. Material is arranged chronologically by day.
    1931: Great Smokey Mountain National Park; Park-to-park highway.
    1932: Great Smokey Mountain National Park; George Washington Bicentennial Celebration; fisheries appropriation; Robeson County Indlans.
    1933: Great Smokey Mountain National Park;; Kings Mountain Battleground National Park;; Ft. Macon State Park;; Uwharrie Hills National Park; Cape Lookout Highway; Robeson County Indians.
    1934: Park-to-park Highway; Uwharrie Hills National Park;; Robeson Coclnty Indians; Wheeler-Howard Bill pertaining to the Indians; Guilford Court Tiouse battleground; relief for fishermen.
    1935: Park-to-park highway; Uwharrie Hills National Park; Guilford Court House battleground; coastal highway; Bentonville battleground; Indians; soil erosion; appropriation cut for park for Negroes in Raleigh, N. C.; Penderlea resettlement project.
    1936: Kings Mountain Battleground National Park; Bentonville Battleground; park-to-park highway; Indians.
    1937: Cherokee Indians; Great Smokey Mountain National Park and the Blue Ridge Parkway; Constitution Scsquicentennial Celebratio n.
    1938: Blue Ridge Parkway.
    1939: Blue Ridge Parkway; Ft. Fisher state historic site; Panama Canal.
    1940: Blue Ridge Parkway; Alamance Battleground.
    1941: Great Smokey Mountain National Park; Alamance Battleground; Roanoke River flood control.
    1942: National parks; manganese production.
    1943: Philippine independence; manganese production.
    1946: Cape Fear River project; flood control.
    - Department of Interior, 1930-1933 (Box 310)
    - Department of Interior, 1933-1934, May (Box 311)
    - Department of Interior, 1934, June-1935, July (Box 312)
    - Department of Interior, 1935, Aug.-1936, undated (Box 313)
    - Department of Interior, 1937-1939, April (Box 314)
    - Department of Interior, 1939, May-1942, Dec. (Box 315)
    - Department of the Interior, 1943 (Oversize-folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Panoramic photograph, Public Hearing, Great Smoky Mountain, National Park Roadway, Washington, DC, Sept 18, 1943
    - Department of Interior, 1943-1946 (Box 316)
  - Wildlife and Conservation Subseries, 1931-1946
    Correspondence and statements deal with efforts to preserve wildlife and natural resources and with the functioning of the Committee on Wildlife and Conservation, of which Bailey was a member. The material concerns the development of wildlife preserves, hunting regulations, and other matters related to conservation. Material is arranged chronologically by day.
    - Wildlife & Conservation, 1931-1943 (Box 316)
    - Wildlife & Conservation, 1943-1946, undated (Box 314)
  - Justice Subseries, 1931-1946
    Correspondence, telegrams, and copies of bills pertain chiefly to routine affairs, such as requests for assistance in obtaining paroles and recommendations for appointments of a juclicial nature, Other correspondence deals with legislation concerning the establishment: and the restructuring of judicial districts in North Carolina. There is also material related to legislation concerning bankruptcy laws and anti-trust laws, to the Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI), and to immigration laws. Some material pertaining to Bailey's private law practice appears in this section, although the bulk of it is found in the Legal Series. Separate folders at the end of this section contain correspondence and printed material related to various Federal anti-lynching bills, and Bailey's opposition to Federal bills as an encroachment on state jurisdiction.
    While the papers for the 1930's are covered by the above description, several other important issues appear in those for the 1940's: FBI appropriations and the activities of the FBI (1940); fifth column activity and bills concerning aliens (1940-1941); the question of the legality of wire tapping by the FBI in time of emergency (1942); and Federal seizure of the Montgomery Ward Company (1944). Material is arranged chronologically by day.
    - Justice, 1931-1932, July (Box 317)
    - Justice, 1932, Aug.-1934, June 6 (Box 318)
    - Justice, 1934, June 7-1936, Sept. (Box 319)
    - Justice, 1936, Oct.-1938, March (Box 320)
    - Justice, 1938, April-1940, April (Box 321)
    - Justice, 1940, May-1942, May (Box 322)
    - Justice, 1942, June-1944, Feb. (Box 323)
    - Justice, 1944, March-1945, March 7 (Box 324)
    - Justice, 1945, March 8-1946, March (Box 325)
    - Justice, 1946, April-Dec., undated (Box 326)
    - Anti-Lynching, 1933, April-1938, Jan. 17 (Box 326)
  - Supreme Court Subseries, 1931-1946
    The bulk of the material in this section consists of constituent correspondence concerning Roosevelt's Court-packing Bill of 1937. An outspoken critic of the reorganization plan, Bailey made several speeches, including The Living Soul of Democracy (February, 1937) and In Defense of the Independence of the Judiciary (July, 1937), and the major portion of the letters deals with Bailey's stand on Roosevelt's proposal. Included are copies and drafts of Bailey's speeches and statements. The material for other years is meagre. There is some correspondence dealing with Supreme Court nominations, such as the replacement of Justice Holmes (1932) and the nominations of Hugo Black (1937), Felix Frankfurter (1939), and Frank Murphy (1940). Much of the material during the 1940's, centering around the two presidential campaigns, deals with proposals supported by Bailey to limit presidential tenure. Material is arranged chronologically by day.
    - Anti-Lynching, 1938, Jan. 18-1940, May (Box 327)
    - Supreme Court, 1931- 1937, Feb. 8 (Box 327)
    - Supreme Court, 1937, Feb. 9-13 (Box 328)
    - Supreme Court, 1937, Feb. 13-15 (Box 329)
    - Supreme Court, 1937, Feb. 15-20 (Box 330)
    - Supreme Court, 1937, Feb. 20-28 (Box 331)
    - Supreme Court, 1937, Feb. (undated)-March 8 (Box 332)
    - Supreme Court, 1937, March 8-18 (Box 333)
    - Supreme Court, 1937, March 19-April 7 (Box 334)
    - Supreme Court, 1937, April 8-May 21 (Box 335)
    - Supreme Court, 1937, May 22-July 13 (Box 336)
    - Supreme Court, 1937, July 13-17 (Box 337)
    - Supreme Court, 1937, July 17-Sept. 30 (Box 338)
    - Supreme Court, 1937, Oct.-Dec. (Box 339)
    - Supreme Court, Hugo Black Nomination (Partial), 1937, Aug. (Box 339)
    - Supreme Court, Statments & Speeches, 1937 & undated (Box 339)
    - Supreme Court, 1938-1946, undated (Box 340)
    - Supreme Court, Constitutional Amendment Limiting Presidential Terms, 1943 (Box 340)
  - Labor and Management Subseries, 1931-1946
    This section is comprised of correspondence, telegrams, copies of bills, statements, speeches, and notes, principally concerning labor legislation and the duties of labor and management. The main focus of legislation during the 1930's concerns various bills to establish maximum hours and to provide a minimum wage and unemployment compensation, the National Industrial Recovery Act (NTRA), and the National Labor Relations Board (NLRB). Correspondence from various labor organizations requested Bailey's support on numerous bills. Other constituent mail opposed the activities of the unions. Much of the latter correspondence concerns the actions of John L. Lewis, the Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO), and sit-dowm strikes. There is also correspondence, 1933, dealing with Secretary of Labor Frances Perkins's statement ahout the shoeless South and Bailey's defense of conditions in the South. The bulk of the material for the 1940's relates to the conflict between labor unions, principally the CIO, and the prosecution of the war. The major question concerned whether the sit-down strikes and demands of the labor unions were jeopardizing the war effort and the postponement of these demands until after the war. Much of the correspondence for 1944 deals with Bailey's proposed Work or Fight Bill, his response to this national dilemma. Correspondence for 1946 deals with the Fair Employment Practices Commission. Although some papers pertain to the regulation of immigration, the major portion of the material is in the State Department and Immigration category of the Foreign Affairs section. Material is arranged chronologically by month.
    1931: Reduction of wages of Federal employees,
    1932: Reduction of wages of Federal employees; Flagner Public Works Bill; Norris Anti-Injunction Bill.
    1933: Black Thirty-hour-Work-Week Bill; Secretary of Labor Frances Perkins's statement about the shoeless South; Section 7A of NIRA (collective bargaining).
    1934: Wagner-Connery Labor Disputes Bill; Section 7A of NIRA; Wagner Labor Relations Bill.
    1935: Wagner Labor Relation Bill; Black Thirty-Hour-Work-week Bill; Kerr Deportation Bill.
    1936: National Textile Act (Ellenbogen Bill); Reynolds Immigration Bill; Kerr Deportation Bill.